<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perswasive to the stricter observation of the Lords day in pursuance of His Majesties pious order and directions to preachers particularly about the observation of the Lord's day, &amp;c. / by Matthew Bryan.</title>
            <author>Bryan, Matthew, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12676361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12676361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 681:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perswasive to the stricter observation of the Lords day in pursuance of His Majesties pious order and directions to preachers particularly about the observation of the Lord's day, &amp;c. / by Matthew Bryan.</title>
                  <author>Bryan, Matthew, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Keble ... and D. Brown ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PERSWASIVE To the Stricter OBSERVATION OF THE LORDS DAY: In purſuance of His MAJESTIES Pious Order and Directions to PREACHERS Particularly about the Obſervation of the LORD's DAY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Matthew Bryan,</hi> L. L. D.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Licens'd</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>June 16t.h. 1686.</date>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Keble</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreeet,</hi> and <hi>D. Brown</hi> at the black <hi>Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65554:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65554:2"/>
            <p>Reverendo admodum In Chriſto Patri ac Domino, D. PETRO Providentiâ Divina WINTONIENSI EPISCOPO, Et nobiliſſimi Ordinis à periſcelide dicti Praeſuli Digniſſimo; Copiarum, ſub Rege maximè pio ac Martyre CAROLO primo, Duci fortiſſimo; In Exilii Miſeriis Benigniſſimi CAROLI Secundi ſervo &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> invicto; Rebellibus Occidentalibus, ſub Rege Sereniſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo JACOBO Secundo, Terrori, Et Armis, &amp; Precibus Regis Regnique Opitulatori, Bonorum Fautori, Improborum Malleo, Eccleſiae Anglicanae Strenuo Vindici Et Ornamento, M. B.</p>
            <p>Hanc de die Dominicâ pie obſervandâ Concionem, coram Londinenſibus habitam, Humillimè &amp; cum devotiſſimâ Veneratione Offert.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:65554:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65554:3"/>
            <head>A PERSWASIVE TO THE Stricter OBSERVATION OF THE LORDS DAY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 20.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Remember the Sabbath Day to keep it holy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>'TIS an old Obſervation, in which there is a great deal of truth, though ſometimes urg'd for very ill ends, particularly to diſcountenance that great Goſpel Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Preaching, <hi>Nil dictum quod non dictum prius:</hi> which I might Engliſh in the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> though ſpoken by him on another account,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no new thing under the Sun.</hi> There is nothing done or ſaid, but it has been done or ſaid already. Tho this might ſeem to ſuperſede all further Inquiries, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to document and inſtruct the World, and diſpence knowledge, and at once upbraid and ſilence the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker, by telling him that what he does is but <hi>actum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere</hi> to do that which is done already; yet certainly, in regard there dwell in us treacherous and unfaithful
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65554:4"/>memories, and dull and drowſie affections, unapt eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Spiritual and Divine Things, it cannot be denied, that an honeſt <hi>Remembrancer</hi> is as neceſſary and uſeful as the moſt eloquent Inſtructer to be imagin'd; which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeems to acknowledge, by magnifying the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> no leſs than three times in one Chapter: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13, 15, <hi>Wherefore I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of theſe things, tho ye know them, and be eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth. Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this Tabernacle, to stir you up, by putting you in remembrance: moreover I will endeavour, that you may be able after my deceaſe to have theſe things alwayes in remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We leſs want the knowledge than the practice of our duties. 'Tis not ſo much the furniſhing our heads with a richer treaſure of ſpeculations, as the profitable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of what we know, that is, or ought to be the great end of Preaching. The inculcating of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therefore muſt needs be both neceſſary and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, the putting men in mind of what they know already. Now amongſt the ſeveral duties which in faithfulneſs I muſt put you in mind of, I think it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable to put you in remembrance of that which this Day, or rather, the Lord of this Day requires of you, <hi>viz.</hi> The hallowing and ſanctifying of the Sabbath; of late ſo much neglected and prophaned amongſt us. Give me leave therefore, following the Example of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to put you in remembrance of theſe things, tho you know them, and be eſtabliſhed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent truth and duty. Duty, may ſome ſay! Ay, would you would ſatisfie us to that! For that's the ſcruple that lies upon our ſpirits. We know indeed, that the firſt day of the Week according to the Scripture computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is enjoyn'd by humane Law, under a Penalty to be kept ſolemn and ſacred for the Worſhip of God, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65554:4"/>ſeems to be contrary to the poſitive command of God held forth in the fourth Commandment: which, by the Example of God himſelf ſeems to intimate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the obſervation of the Seventh Day from the Creation, as the Sabbath of the Lord to be kept by the Lord's people. Now the <hi>Fourth Commandment,</hi> you ſay, is of moral and perpetual obligation, part of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which you ſay, is a Rule of Life to a Believer; and every Sunday we are taught after pronouncing of this Commandment to beg mercy and pardon for our breach of it, and ſtrength better to keep it for the time to come, in that ſhort ejaculation, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, and inoline our hearts to keep this Law.</hi> Now it ſeems ſtrange, that we ſhould be oblig'd to a duty ſo ſeemingly contrary to the <hi>Fourth Commandment:</hi> which yet we are taught to acknowledge obedience to, and beg God to incline our hearts to keep it; when as at that very time it ſeems to us that we openly break it, not keeping that Day which is there mentioned.</p>
            <p>This, I confeſs, has been a ſcruple that has troubled the ſpirits of many, and drawn ſome into a practical error. For ſatisfaction therefore of the ſcrupulous, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the conſcionable obſervers of the Chriſtian Sabbath, I ſhall labour to ſhew you the indiſpenſable Obligation of it: And to that end, I have for my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject pitch'd my thoughts on the Words of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment which ſeem to ſpeak ſo much againſt it: but before I have done, I hope, you'll conclude with me that the obſervation of the Chriſtian Sabbath is not inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the duty held forth in the Text, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to this Argument I ſhall do theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew you the divine Inſtitution of the Chriſtian Sabbath, which we now celebrate, that to obſerve and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65554:5"/>keep it is our duty, and that in obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhew you the manner how the Duty is to be performed, wherein the right and due Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the day conſiſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, I ſhall make ſome reflection on the whole by Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. My firſt undertaking ſhall be to ſhew you the Divine Inſtitution of the Chriſtian Sabbath, which we now celebrate; that to obſerve and keep it is our duty, and that in Obedience to the Command of God.</p>
            <p>And truely Brethren, this Truth ought to be well ſettled and fixed in our minds, as that which will migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily perſwade us to the conſcionable performance of the duty of the day; for if I apprehend it to be only of humane Inſtitution, and the Command of Man, how will it abate the value and eſteem, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſhould have for it, ſtrangely leſſen my Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reverence! how will it damp my zeal, and clip the wings of my riſing and exulting Joy, which would be the reſult of this conſideration,—<hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made,</hi>—the inference would then be eaſie and natural, <hi>Let us rejoyce, and be glad in it!</hi> Sirs! Whilſt I believe that the Obſervation of this day, is but the Command of a mortal dying man, my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem is no more for it than for another day: But when I believe, and am perſwaded, and conſider, that 'tis the Command of the God that made me, the God that redeemed me, and the God that ſhall ſhortly come to judge me; O how will this raiſe my mind, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven my affections, and check my floath, and quicken my zeal, and awaken my Conſcience to a ſenſe and conſcionable performance of my duty! And therefore I would willingly fix this as a great truth and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable principle in your minds, that to obſerve and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65554:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>keep this day in your Duty, and that in Obedience to the Command of God. And here the better to make way to what I intend, I muſt premiſe theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Fourth Commandment is moral, <hi>i. e.</hi> of perpetual Obligation, as to the ſubſtance of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our Saviour Chriſt, who was Lord of the Sabbath, had power to make what alteration he pleas'd, as to the ceremonial part of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Fourth Commandment is moral, <hi>i. e.</hi> of perpetual Obligation, as to the ſubſtance of it; (tho ceremonial for Circumſtance) if not, then there are but nine Commandments under the Goſpel (for what was purely ceremonial relating to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is aboliſhed) and in vain are we taught to pray after the rehearſal of this Commandment; <hi>Lord have mercy us, and incline our hearts to keep this Law,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To keep ſome Time holy the to Lord for his Solemn Service, is abſolutely moral, which the Light of Nature prompts men to. Now 'tis plain, a Sabbath God muſt have by the perpetual Ordinance of the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. <hi>Remember to keep Holy the Sabbath Day, i.e.</hi> that day which for the time being, God hath marked out and appointed for his own. And he hath declar'd his will concerning the limitation of it, <hi>Six days ſhalt thou labour, and do all that thou haſt to do, but the ſeventh is the Sabbath.</hi> The Seventh from the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was enjoyn'd to be kept by the <hi>Jews</hi> in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Creation, according to God's own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: <hi>In ſix days the Lord made Heaven and Earth; and reſted the Seventh Day;</hi> which was obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the giving of the Law on <hi>Sinai.</hi> Well but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians obſerve not this ſeventh day which the <hi>Jews</hi> did, do they then break the Commandment? God forbid! no, they do not break the Commandment; and this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65554:6"/>will appear by the ſecond thing which I have to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That our Saviour Chriſt, who was Lord of the Sabbath had power to make what alteration he pleas'd, as to the Ceremonial part of the Commandment. Our Saviour tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> 2.28. <hi>that the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.</hi> He was ſo indeed, for 'twas he that made the VVorld, and gave the Law on <hi>Sinai:</hi> And he ſhew'd the true uſe of the Sabbath, that 'twas made for Man, and not Man for the Sabbath, and as Lord of it, he had power to make what Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration he pleas'd. Now the Alteration he made was about the circumſtance of time, not as to the matter of the Commandment, one day in ſeven, but as to the Circumſtance of time, <hi>i. e.</hi> which day in ſeven he pleas'd. Now if I can prove to you that our Saviour Chriſt alter'd the circumſtance of time, and that that time which the Chriſtians now obſerve is that Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I hope you'l conclude with me that the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian Sabbath is no breach of the Fourth Commandment, but an indiſpenſable duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon the Church of Chriſt, and that it is ſo will appear by theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt I ſhall draw from the immediate au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of our Saviour, who, to let the VVorld know that his pleaſure was to tranſlate the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath, which was Saturday, the ſeventh from the Creation, to the firſt day of the VVeek, was pleas'd,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To Honour this day with his Reſurrection from the dead, which was on the firſt day of the VVeek when he had finiſh'd the work of our Redemption, as he had before on the beginning of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath finiſh'd the work of our Creation. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſlept its laſt in the Grave with Chriſt, and at his Reſurrection immediately enter'd the Lords day; from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65554:6"/>the very day of the Reſurrection of Chriſt St.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep. ad Jan.</hi> 19. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> derives the beginning of the Goſpel Sabbath. <hi>The Lords day,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by the Reſurrection of Chriſt, was declar'd to be the Chriſtians day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dominicum diem quem vobis Salvatoris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctri Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, &amp;c. Id. de Verb. Apoſt. ſerm.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>and from that very time it began to be celebrated as the Chriſtians Feſtival.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the Firſt day of our Saviours appearing to his Diſciples, and during the forty days he remain'd up on Earth after his Reſurrection, he appear'd to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples uſually upon the firſt day of the VVeek, and gave them Orders about the things concerning his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He honoured this day with the firſt miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1, &amp;c. <hi>When the day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt was fully come, &amp;c.</hi> Pentecoſt, that year, fell on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the firſt day of the VVeek: VVhich I thus plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove to you. There were three Solemn Feaſts which were appointed the <hi>Jews</hi> every year; The Feaſt of the Paſſeover: The Feaſt of Harveſt: And the Feaſt of Tabernacles; as you may read <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.14, 15.</p>
            <p>The Feaſt of Harveſt (ſtyl'd <hi>Deut</hi> 16.9. the Feaſt of Weeks) was fifty days after the Feaſt of the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.15, 16. This Feaſt of VVeeks is the ſame which St. <hi>Luke</hi> calls here Pentecoſt; which is a Greek VVord fignifying the fiftieth day, and retain'd in our Engliſh Tranſlation, which time we now call <hi>Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day:</hi> VVhich we obſerve is always ſeven weeks after <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Now this day, which was ſeven weeks after the Paſſeover, fell that year on Sunday, when the Holy Ghoſt deſcended, as will appear if you conſult <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.14, 31. Where you find that the day our Saviour was Crucified was the day of the preparation of the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and the next day was the Sabbath, on which the Paſſeover that year was celebrated, which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtil'd an high day <hi>v.</hi> 31. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65554:7"/>day, i.e.</hi> a very ſolemn day in reſpect of the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a double celebrity: the Sabbath, and the Feaſt of the Paſſeover.</p>
            <p>Now reckon ſeven Weeks from the Paſſeover, which was <hi>Saturday,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbath, to the day of Pentecoſt incluſively, which makes up the compleat number of fifty days, and you'll find that it fell on <hi>Sunday</hi> the firſt day of the Week, on which the Holy Ghoſt diſcended, as it were, to give birth to the Chriſtian Sabbath, which had it's conception at Chriſts Reſurrection. And <hi>Grotius</hi> noteth from <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.1. that it was the day the Law was given on, and ſo on which the Spirit was given for the new Law.</p>
            <p>So much for Chriſts immediate Authority. If any ſay that all this is but conjectural, that it ſerves to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but not to prove the point in hand, ſpeaking the probability, but not the certainty of the thing; I have ſomewhat to offer in the next place that will put the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of all doubt; and therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. My ſecond Argument I draw from the Authority of the Apoſtles, who did nothing of themſelves but by commiſſion from Chriſt, Mal. 28.19, 20. <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you: and lo, I am with you alway even unto the end of the World.</hi> How could he be with them when he was to be taken from them, and depart into Heaven: He tells them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. where he promiſes to ſend his Spirit, as his Vicar General, to ſupply his place, and abſence, and direct them about all things relating to his Kingdome. <hi>But the Comforter which is the Holy Ghoſt whom the Father will ſend in my name he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you, and</hi> Chap. 16.13, 14. <hi>When he the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you into all truth: for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf, but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65554:7"/>whatſoever he ſhall hear that ſhall he ſpeak. He ſhall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie me: for he ſhall receive of mine and ſhall ſhew it unto you.</hi> So that what the Apoſtles did they did by Divine Warrant. Now we have both Apoſtolical precept and practiſe to warrant the obſervation of the day.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Precept, 1 Cor. 16.1. <hi>As I have ordained in the Churches of</hi> Galatia, <hi>ſo do ye:</hi> and what that Ordinance was, he tells them, v. 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the Week let every one of you lay by him in ſtore as God has proſper'd him, that there may be no gathering when I come.</hi> He ordains their Collections for the poor Saints, and oblations ſhould be on that day. And why ſhould that day be the Collection day rather than any other, had it not been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd holy in thoſe times, and that Chriſtians did uſe on that day to aſſemble? The collection therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enjoyn'd on that day, and that in the weekly returns of it (for the collection was not to be made at once, and no more, but time after time, till it ſwell'd to a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, gathering a Treaſure as the greek word ſignifies, adding ſomething weekly, as God had proſper'd every man) this, I ſay, is an argument, that the day was celebrated as the Chriſtian Sabbath, the work being ſo ſuitable to the day, and then moſt effectually promoted by the opportunity that offer'd it ſelf through the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous aſſembly of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>There is one thing objected againſt the validity of this place for the proof of the point in hand, and that is the Greek phraſe, which the Objectors ſay is not truly tranſlated, <hi>the firſt day of the Week,</hi> the words in the Greek being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which word for word is, on one of the Sabbaths. So that, ſay they, the Apoſtle intended the collection ſhould be made on the Sabbath day, the ſeventh, and not the firſt day of the Week.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that the Tranſlation is good, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65554:8"/>warrantable,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. Hom.</hi> 43. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> obſerve; yea St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> interprets it the Lords day. The word Sabbath is oftentimes put for the whole Week, which is ſignified by that Notion. <hi>Lev.</hi> 15.23. <hi>Seven Sabbaths ſhall be compleat, i. e.</hi> ſeven Weeks. So St. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.12. <hi>I faſt twice in the week;</hi> in the Greek 'tis, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, twice in the Sabbath. And 'tis obſervable that the ſame Phraſe is uſed concerning the day of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is render'd without any objection againſt it the firſt day of the Week: And ſo St. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.1. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1. There is the like Phraſe in the Greek, and the like Tranſlation in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Now they may as well deny the Reſurrection of Chriſt to be on the firſt day of the Week, as the Chriſtian Aſſemblies to be on that day by force of the ſame Objection, the Phraſe being in each place the ſame, and therefore muſt needs have the ſame ſignification. And St. <hi>Mark</hi> ſeems ſo to expound the other Evangeliſts, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which cannot poſſibly with any ſenſe be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Sabbath, but the firſt day of the Week: and the Greek Scholiaſt confidently renders <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> on which the Apoſtles were wont to keep their Aſſemblies; which is the next thing that we are to take notice of and inquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their practice. We find in the 2d. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for religious exerciſes on the firſt day of the Week, the uſual ſolemn time of their meeting in honour and memory of their Lords Reſurrection. And <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. We read that upon the firſt day of the Week, when the Diſciples came together to break Bread (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental or Euchariſtical Bread) St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preached to them ready to depart on the morrow.</p>
            <p>'Tis true we have but a few hints in Scripture of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65554:8"/>obſervation of the day; which is enough however to ſignifie the uſage of the Church then; there being no more need for the Apoſtles, to inform the Chriſtians and others of that time that the firſt day of the Week was the Chriſtians day for the publick and ſolemn Worſhip of God, and religious exerciſes, than for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man to write a Hiſtory to inform his Country men, that <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> is kept in <hi>England</hi> as the Chriſtian Sabbath, and that the Word of God is Preached, and the Lords Supper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred on that day: it being matter of fact, of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and notorious uſage. Yea into ſo great Reputation, and ſuch general and common uſage, was the obſervation of this day grown amongſt the Chriſtians, even in the Apoſtles times, that it had obtain'd a peculiar name, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to the Original and occaſion of it: as the Apoſtle St. <hi>John</hi> obſerves, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I was in the ſpirit on the Lords day,</hi> in the ſpirit, <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſpiritual Exerciſes and Meditations: on the Lords day, <hi>i. e.</hi> the firſt day of the Week, in which the Lord roſe from the dead. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, St. <hi>John</hi> does not ſay, on the day which is worthy to be call'd the Lords day, but he ſpeaks it as a Notion or Phraſe of general and common uſe, a Title given to the day, a known diſcription of it, whereby they might eaſily underſtand what day he meant: <hi>The Lords day,</hi> ſo called, either becauſe Chriſt roſe on that day, and it was by the Church peculiarly dedicated to his honour; or it is ſo called as the Sacrament is called <hi>Coena Dominica, the Lords ſupper;</hi> and the Lords Prayer <hi>Oratio Dominica:</hi> becauſe the Lord inſtituted the one, and taught, and commanded the uſe of the other.
<note place="margin">Athanaſ. Homil. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For ſo S. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> ſaith expreſly, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>our Lord tranſlated the Sabbath to the Lords day.</hi> Whether he did this immediately by himſelf, or by his Apoſtles inſpired by him all comes to one. That it was ſo tranſlated is evident, and a Chriſtian Name
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65554:9"/>given it, being not call'd the Sabbath, (and when we call it ſo, ſtiling it the Chriſtian Sabbath, it is not ſtrictly and properly, but analogically, and by way of alluſion to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath, which was a day of reſt) but the proper, and peculiar, and Evangelical Name is the Lords day; which the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtil'd the firſt day, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Sunday. But it matters not much by what Name we call it, whether Sabbath, or Sunday, or the Firſt Day, ſo that we allow the divine right, and Inſtitution, and obſervation of it: Only I muſt obſerve to you that the Lords day is the moſt proper, and peculiar, and Evangelical Notion; which was obſerv'd and us'd, not only in the Apoſtles times, but in the ſucceeding Ages of the Church; which is an hiſtorical Evidence of the divine Inſtitution of the day, that it was not inſtituted by the Church ſucceeding the Apoſtles, but by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, and the uſage derived to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages of the Church, by Apoſtolical Tradition; and the day generally obſerved by the Church immediately after the Apoſtles days, and ſo forward, as I could ſhew you at large by the Teſtimony of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> who was St. <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciple, makes it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The Queen, the Lady paramount among the other week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly days. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. After the Sabbath let every Friend of Chriſt make the Lords day a Solemn Feſtival, ſays the ſame <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Upon the Sunday <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a common aſſembly both of Citizens and common people is held, &amp;c. ſays <hi>Juſt. Mart. Apol.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Upon that day (<hi>i. e.</hi> Sunday) we Chriſtians meet together in the common Aſſembly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſays <hi>Tertullian Apol. cap.</hi> 39.</p>
                  <p>We Chriſtians aſſemble our ſelves with much diligence, upon the Lords day, to praiſe God, &amp;c. <hi>Clemt. Rom. Conſt. Ap l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 63. St. <hi>Baſil de Spir. Sanct.</hi> 27. Numbers the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Lords day amongſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Traditions. And St. <hi>Auguſtine's</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Golden Rule proves it to be ſo.<hi>-Quod univerſa tenet Eccleſia, nec Conciliis inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed ſemper retentum eſt, non niſi autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Apoſtolica traditum rectiſſimè credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aug. de Bapt. c. Donatiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24 Plin. Ep 97. <hi>ad Trajanum. lib. dec. p.</hi> 434. <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſoliti ſtato die ante lucem convenire: car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Chriſto, quaſi Deo, dicere ſecum invicem ſe<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Ancients. But I ſhall only take particular notice of the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of an Enemy, as to the matter of fact, that the Obſervation of the day was as old as the Apoſtles, and that is the famous Heathen <hi>Pliny,</hi> who inform'd the Emperor <hi>Trajan</hi> (in whoſe Reign the Apoſtle St. <hi>John</hi> liv'd) that it was the uſe of Chriſtians on a ſtated day (by which he could mean no other than the Lords day) to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ſing their <hi>Hymnos ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacanos,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65554:9"/>their Hymns to Chriſt, as God, before day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>break, and to bind themſelves by a Sacrament not to do any wickedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the Teſtimony of a great Heathen, whoſe report as an Hiſtorian is not to be queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Nay the obſervation of this day was ſo taken notice of by the Heathen in the Primitive perſecutions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Imperial Edict or Canon of Council enjoyn'd it, that it became a conſtant interogatory to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when brought upon their Tryal and Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Have you kept the Lords day?</hi> To which their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was ever ready, I cannot intermit it, for I am a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and the Law of God prompts me to it.</p>
            <p>Now put theſe things together, the hiſtorical Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which occur in Scripture of the Apoſtolical Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and Obſervation of the day, and their Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of it in others (for certainly they would not have approv'd of it, but vigorouſly oppos'd it, had it been an uſurpation, and contrary to the mind of Chriſt) theſe things, I ſay, together with the concurrent teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſucceeding Ages of the Church, and not only of Friends, but Enemies too, I think ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prove the Apoſtolical Obſervation of the day, and conſequently the Divine Inſtitution of it, and that in obedience to the Command of God in this precept, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it Holy;</hi> which may be prov'd by an Enumeration or induction of particulars; what Chriſt the Son of God did, that God the Father did, who ſent him into the World; what the Spirit, the Holy Ghoſt did, that Chriſt, who ſent him, did; and what the Apoſtles, who were inſpir'd with the Spirit did, that the Spirit himſelf did: Thus in their firſt Council, Act. 15.28: <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us;</hi> and the Spirit was to lead them into all Truth, and bring all things to their remembrance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65554:10"/>Now I have prov'd to you both by Scripture and Hiſtory that the Apoſtles did command, and inſtitute, and approve of the Obſervation of the Lords Day: And if they did it the Holy Ghoſt did it, and if the Holy Ghoſt did it Chriſt the Son did it, and if Chriſt did it, God the Father himſelf did it, who here commands us, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it Holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that there are two things whereon the Divine Right of the Lords Day is founded: Upon the moral Equity of the Fourth Commandment, and upon Evangelical Inſtitution. Our Church reduceth the Inſtitution of this day as a week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day to the Fourth Commandment; and as the firſt day of the Week ſhe foundeth it upon Apoſtolical practice and tradition. For which I might refer you to the Words of the Homily of the place and time of Prayer. <hi>As concerning the time which Almighty God has appointed his people to aſſemble together ſolemnly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Book of</hi> Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies <hi>p.</hi> 214.</note> 
               <hi>it doth appear by the Fourth Commandment of God:</hi> Remember, <hi>ſaith God,</hi> that thou keep Holy the Sabbath day. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which day, as is plain in the</hi> Acts of the Apoſtles, <hi>the people accuſtomably reſorted together, and heard diligently the Law and the Prophets read among them. And albeit this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God doth not bind Chriſtian people ſo ſtraitly to obſerve and keep the utter Ceremonies of the Sabbath day, as it was given unto the</hi> Jews, <hi>as touching the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing of Work and Labour in time of great neceſſity, and as touching the preciſe keeping of the ſeventh day after the manner of the</hi> Jews. <hi>For we keep now the firſt day, which is our Sunday; and make that our Sabbath, that is, our day of reſt, in the honour of our Saviour Chriſt, who as upon that day roſe from death, conquering the ſame moſt triumphantly: Yet notwithſtanding whatſoever is found in the Commandment appertaining to the Law of Nature, as a thing most godly, moſt juſt, and needful for the ſetting forth of Gods Glory, it ought to be retained and kept of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65554:10"/>all good Chriſtian people. And therefore by this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we ought to have a time, as one day in the Week, wherein we ought to reſt, yea from our lawful and needful Works.</hi> Again, <hi>God hath given expreſs charge to all men, that upon the Sabbath day, which is now our Sunday, they ſhould ceaſe from all Weekly and Work day labour,</hi> &amp;c. And a little after, <hi>God doth not only Command the Obſervation of this Holy day, &amp;c.</hi> And again a little after, <hi>Thus it may plainly appear, that God's Will and Commandment was to have a ſolemn time and ſtanding day in the Week, wherein the people ſhould come together, and have in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance his wonderful benefits, and to render him thanks for them, as appertaineth to loving, kind, and obedient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This Example and Commandment of God, the godly Chriſtian people began to follow immediately after the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of our Lord Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>and began to chooſe them a ſtanding day of the week to come together in: Yet not the ſeventh day, which the</hi> Jews <hi>kept; but the Lords day, the day of the Lord's Reſurrection, the day after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, which is the firſt day of the Week. Of the which day mention is made by St.</hi> Paul <hi>on this wiſe. In the firſt day of the Sabbath, let every man lay up what he thinketh good: Meaning for the poor. By the firſt day of the Sabbath is meant our Sunday, which is the firſt day after the</hi> Jews <hi>ſeventh day.</hi> And <hi>in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps it is more plain, whereas St.</hi> John <hi>ſaith, I was in the Spirit upon the Lords day. Sithence which time Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath always, in all ages, without any gainſaying, uſed to come together upon the Sunday, to Celebrate and honour the Lords bleſſed Name,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are the words of the ſaid Homily, which ſufficiently declare the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (of which we are members) in this point.</p>
            <p>To which, as not impertinent I will add the words of the Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Polity. <hi>We are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65554:11"/>bound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hook. Eccleſ. Polit. l.</hi> 5.</note> ſays he, <hi>to account the ſanctification of one day in ſeven a Duty which God's immutable Law doth exact for ever; altho with us the day be changed, in regard of a new revolution, begun by our Saviour Chriſt; yet the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of time continueth, which was before, by way of a perpetual homage never to be diſpenſed withal nor remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond thing which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The manner how the duty is to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, wherein the right and due obſervation of the day conſiſts. And this we may learn from the words of the Text, from the Notions here <hi>[Sabbath, and keep Holy.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To keep holy or to ſanctifie is not to infuſe or put any moral inrinſick Holineſs into the day, as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit does infuſe holineſs into the hearts of men: But to ſanctifie here, is to ſeparate from a common and prophane, to an Holy and religious Uſe. And thus both God and Man are ſaid to ſanctifie.</p>
            <p>God ſanctifies by appointing and ſeparating a thing from a common to an holy and religious uſe: And Man ſanctifies by applying to ſuch holy and divine uſe as God appointed. And to what uſe this day is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified or ſeparated we may learn from the Word <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> which ſignifies a day or time of reſt: A reſt from bodily labours, from the Works of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular calling; but always with this reſervation, that we muſt make allowances for Works of neceſſity and Charity, to which poſitive Laws muſt always give Place:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Mat.</hi> 12.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> (all Judaizing ſeverities, being to be renounced and deteſted.) which our Saviour teacheth in the inſtance of his Diſciples gathering the ears of Corn, a Work of neceſſity to ſatisfie hunger,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 10.11. &amp;c.</note> and healing the Sick and Lame,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.16.</note> a work of Mercy and Charity, on the Sabbath day, Which indeed the <hi>Jews</hi> quarrel'd with,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65554:11"/>accounting it unlawful on the Sabbath day. Which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious ſtrictneſs of theirs our Saviour reproves by the allow'd Inſtance of Mercy and Charity to a Beaſt that falls into a Ditch on the Sabbath day;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.3, 4.</note> much more then <hi>à fortiori</hi> ought it to be extended to Man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27.</note> the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Creature, for whom the <hi>Sabbath was made, and not Man for the Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that making theſe allowances, for works of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and Charity, it muſt be a day of reſt from bodily labours. But that's not all; it muſt not be a bodily reſt and no more, for then the Ox and the Aſs keep as good a Sabbath as we; but the reſt muſt be conſecrated to God, it muſt be an holy reſt, a vacation from the works of our particular, that we may attend thoſe of our general Calling. The day muſt be ſpent in religious Exerciſes, and performances, both publick and private, as Divine Service in the Church, Reading, and Preaching, and Hearing the Word of God, and Celebrating, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the holy Sacrament, and Catechiſing, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> together with Prayer, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Scriptures and other good Books, and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing in private Families, viſiting the ſick, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Poor, and meditating on the Works and Word of God, our Creation and Redemption, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preparing our ſelves and our domeſtick Relatives for another World. <hi>God hath given expreſs charge to all men;</hi> (ſaith the Homily before mention'd) <hi>that upon the Sabbath day, which is now our Sunday, they ſhould ceaſe from all weekly and work day labour; to the intent that like as God himſelf wrought ſix dayes and reſted the Seventh, and bleſſed and ſanctified it, and conſecrated it to quietneſs and reſt from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: even ſo Gods obedient people ſhould uſe the Sunday ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, and reſt from the common and daily buſineſs, and alſo give themſelves wholly to heavenly Exerciſes of God's true Religion and Service. So that God doth not only command the obſervation of this holy day, but alſo by his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65554:12"/>example doth ſtir and provoke us to the diligent keeping of the ſame. Good natural Children will not only become obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent to the commandment of their parents, but alſo have a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent eye to their doings and gladly follow the ſame. So if we will be the Children of our heavenly Father, we muſt be careful to keep the Chriſtian Sabbath day, which is the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, not only for that it is God's expreſs commandment; but alſo to declare our ſelves to be loving Children, in following the example of our gracious Lord and Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus briefly of the ſecond thing which I propounded to ſpeak to; I come now in the Third and Laſt place, to make ſome Reflections on what hath been ſaid by Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine of the Obſervation of the Lords day ſerves</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Reproof; and that of three ſorts of Perſons,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe who keep the Jewiſh, but not the Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe who keep both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And eſpecially thoſe who keep none at all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe who keep the Jewiſh but not the Chriſtian Sabbath: which is the Errour of thoſe Chriſtians who miſtake the ceremonial for the moral Obligation of the <hi>Fourth Commandement:</hi> Suppoſing the Morality of the Commandment to conſiſt in keeping the Seventh day, which God enjoyn'd the Jews; whereas that is the poſitive and ceremonial part of the Commandment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the Oeconomy and political State of the Jews, binding them only, and not the Gentiles, and no longer neither then till the entrance and ſettling of the Goſpel State by Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt. And now for any Chriſtian, whether Jew or Gentile, to keep the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law, is in effect to deny Chriſt, and to expect a Meſſiah yet to come; to keep the ſhadow and reject the ſubſtance; the Ceremonial Law being but the ſhadow of good things to come, but the body is of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65554:12"/>
            <p>Secondly, they likewiſe are to be blamed who keep both days, the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian too. Thus the <hi>Ebionites</hi> of old, who being Apes of others, would keep the Sabbath with the Jews, and <hi>Sunday</hi> with the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But truely, I think our Charity ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to theſe as the more harmleſly erroneous, and more pardonable Offenders; in regard partly through miſtake and weakneſs, partly out of a ſcrupulous and tender Conſcience, they keep both days, probably with an honeſt deſign and deſire, and not out of peeviſh ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy that they may be in the right. But though they are excuſable <hi>à tanto,</hi> yet not <hi>à toto:</hi> 'tis plainly an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and inconſiſtent with our duty enjoyn'd in the <hi>Fourth Commandment,</hi> which requires but one day in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as God's peculiar, and allows the other ſix for our own labours; and to keep two Sabbaths in a Week ſeems to be wiſe above what is written, and to do more than is our duty. And though, the Apoſtles, and the Chriſtians with them, did for a time keep both days, that is, the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian Sabbath, yet that was for the ſame reaſon that Circumciſion was for a while kept a foot, <hi>viz.</hi> to comply with the weakneſs, and prejudice of the Jews, (to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays he became as a Jew that that he might gain the Jews) and to give the aboliſh'd Ceremonies, which were dead with Chriſt, an honourable burial, but</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. And eſpecially they are worthy of reproof who keep no Sabbath at all; or at leaſt in ſuch a manner as is equivalent to the not keeping of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt. Some there are that keep no Sabbath at all, as the Atheiſt and prophane Worldling. There are a ſort of men who ſufficiently declare themſelves to be Atheiſts and Mammoniſts, who fear not to deny God his due, who have no manner of ſenſe of duty, which they owe to the Lords day, but purpoſely and deſignedly oppoſe, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65554:13"/>ſlight, and prophane it. If they have any buſineſs to do, any viſit to make, not out of Charity but comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; any journey to go, any Accounts to make up, any Letters to write, or the like; God's day muſt be the time for't; tho it might be confeſſedly as well done on any other day of the week, no neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling. Yea when no buſineſs offers, they will frame excuſes to keep 'em from God's houſe, either they muſt ſleep, or play, or drink, or talk, or walk away the time, which others devoutly ſpend in the publick Service of God, and preparing themſelves for another World. Nothing ſo irkſome and tireſome as what God Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; no time ſo lies upon hand as on that day; they know not what to do; they are weary of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and of the time, and ſtudy for ſome diverſion or other, and blame the lingring time, and wiſh and ſay with thoſe in the Prophet, <hi>When will the Sabbath be over, that we may ſet forth Corn, that we may be at our traffick and Trades again?</hi> And if they are prevail'd with by ſome devouter Neighbour, or an argument <hi>ab inutili &amp; damno,</hi> which the Law preſents them upon total neglect to go to the houſe of God, how tedious and burdenſome is the time there? What an inſipid taſteleſs thing is the Service of God? How do they tacitely chide the ſlow-pac'd ſands in the Preachers Glaſs, and grow angry with him if he exceeds his hour, when the time ſpent on ſports, and pleaſures, and buſineſs of the World is thought too ſwift of foot? An hour ſpent at a Sermon, yea and upon God's day too, is thought too long, when a play of three or four hours is done too ſoon. If this is not an evidence of an Atheiſtical and worldly ſpirit I know not what is. Is this the Character of a man that fears and loves the honour of God? What and delight in nothing leſs, ſhun his company, and fly from his preſence, and avoid Communion with him,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65554:13"/>and break his Laws and ſacrilegiouſly rob him of his juſt dues: which the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> wonders at <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, <hi>Will aman rob God?</hi> Will he rob God that made him, and governs him, and that has power to bleſs or to curſe him, to ſave or to deſtroy him. This is a thing was never heard of amongſt the moſt barbarous and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous, whomſoever they rob, they will not rob their God.</p>
            <p>The primitive Chriſtians I am ſure abhor'd ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge. But O how unlike the Primitive ſanctity is the practice of this ſacrilegious Age, this perverſe and adulterous generation? <hi>They</hi> made it their meat and drink to do the Will of God, <hi>they</hi> would not be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for a World from the publick Aſſemblies of the Saints on the Lords day, unleſs invincible neceſſity did hinder, and would not depart thence without the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian viaticum,</hi> without the heavenly <hi>Repaſt and Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet,</hi> the Communion of the <hi>Body and Blood</hi> of their dear Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus they kept the Sabbath indeed not doing their own but the Work of God, and call'd, and accounted <hi>the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honourable, and did honour him, not doing their own ways, nor finding their own pleaſures, nor ſpeaking their own Words.</hi> But at what lame, and deficient, and prepoſterous rate do the generality of Chriſtians now keep the day? They keep it very well, if to keep it be to break it, if to ſanctifie it be to prophane it, if to obſerve and honour it, be to ſlight and pollute it. They keep it very well who ſeldome or never attend the publick Worſhip, and are as careleſs of private Duties; they keep it very well indeed who never receiv'd the Sacrament in their lives, or at leaſt obſerve it as a Paſſeover Feaſt in the trueſt Notion of it, as to the time, <hi>i. e.</hi> once in a year; and that to ſtill the clamours of the Law and their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65554:14"/>not being mov'd from a principle of Love to their Redeemer, to <hi>do this in remembrance of him;</hi> not at all affected with what St. <hi>Paul</hi> inſinuates and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends in theſe VVords, <hi>as often as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lords Death till he come,</hi> but</p>
            <p>Secondly, There are others that are partial Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the day, who think it their duty to go to Church and be preſent at divine Service, and attend the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ordinances and performances (and in that they do well, and are to be commended, and I wiſh there were more that did ſo) but then they think that the duty of the day is over; they take little care to prepare themſelves or their Families before they go to Church, and as little when they come from thence, that they may digeſt what they have heard and receiv'd there, by Catechizing, Examining, Meditation, Conference, reading, ſinging of Pſalms, and Prayer; which are the private and Domeſtick duties of the day. The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath muſt be our <hi>delight,</hi> on which we muſt not <hi>think our own thoughts, nor ſpeak our own words, nor do our own Works, nor find our own Pleaſures,</hi> that is, we muſt forbear and withdraw our minds and affections,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 15.13.</note> from ſuch ſtudies and employments upon that day, whereby the ſame might be polluted or prophaned. It muſt be ſacred to God, and be ſpent in his ſervice, and in Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him; which is to be promoted not only by publick, but private Duties.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide there are ſome that pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very careful and conſcientious in the performance of private duties, but neglect the publick, vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining and concluding, that they can pray and read the Scriptures as well at home as at Church, yea and read as good a Sermon, (perhaps better) as they can hear at Church. Admit it to be true, yet one duty muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65554:14"/>not juſtle out another. The ſame God who has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded private has injoyn'd alſo publick duties. The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could undoubtedly read the Law, and did, and pray too, in their private Tents and Houſes; yet by God's Command they muſt repair to the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in the Wilderneſs, and the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to hear the Law and attend the publick Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Our great Evangelical Lawgiver, does not only command his Diſciples to pray in ſecret but openly, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the Congregation, not only in the Cloſet, but the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue and Temple, to which he invites his Diſciples both for publick Prayer and Preaching, not only by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, but example too. He bids them hear the Scribes and Phariſees which ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair, and does him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Preach in the Synagogue and the Temple, to which he ſhew'd ſo great a Veneration in obedience to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient precept, <hi>ye ſhall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my Sanctuary,</hi> that he exercis'd an unuſual ſeverity in purging it of the pollutions and abuſes which he obſerved there. <hi>He made a ſcourge of ſmall Cords,</hi> and whipt out the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners of it, ſtyling them Thieves and Robbers, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly polluting that holy place, dedicated to holy U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>It is written, my Houſe ſhall be call'd an Houſe of Prayer, but ye have made it a Den of Thieves,</hi> Mat. 21.13.</p>
            <p>So that, he that has commanded private, has injoyn'd alſo publick duties: his publick Ordinances were not made in vain: to each of which duties we muſt pay a due reſpect: Our obedience muſt be regular and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. <hi>I have reſpect unto all thy Commandments,</hi> ſays <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> One duty muſt not excommunicate another. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick muſt not juſtle out private, nor private publick du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And he that allows it to be ſo, is but a partialiſt in Religion, and does his duty but by halves, and is in God's account as if he did it not all.</p>
            <p>A partial obſerving of the Sabbath is but little better
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65554:15"/>than a total neglecting of it, the not keeping it duely, equivalent to the not keeping any, at leaſt a very lame and imperfect Obſervation, as it will one day appear by the Cenſure of <hi>Him</hi> who judgeth not as man judgeth, who will not be mock'd or impos'd upon with fallacious appearances, or a partial piece meal Obedience.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee who are juſtly reprovable by this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe who keep the Jewiſh, but not the Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe who keep both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And eſpecially, thoſe who keep none at all: or at leaſt in ſuch a manner as is equivalent to the not keeping of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Give me leave now to add a word of Exhortation, which may beſuitable to all; at leaſt none ought to be offended at it: not the conſcionable Obſervers of the Lord's day; for to admoniſh, and warn, and exhort them to do the duty which they do already, is but <hi>monendo laudare,</hi> to praiſe whilſt we admoniſh; and the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are us'd to perſwade them that do not, may ſerve at leaſt to remember, and confirm and eſtabliſh thoſe that do their duty. And then for the looſe, and prophane, and careleſs, (whom I will ſuppoſe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of their duty, and that they ought to keep the Chriſtian Sabbath) exhortations and perſwaſions muſt needs be as neceſſary and ſuitable for them, as Phyſick is for the ſick and diſeaſed. <hi>I beſeech you therefore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> (to uſe St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words to the <hi>Hebrews) ſuffer the word of Exhortation;</hi> and that it may be the more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent and ſucceſsful to the end for which it is deſign'd, <hi>viz.</hi> to perſwade Chriſtians to a due and conſcionable Obſervation of the Lords day, I will lay before you theſe Arguments or Motives drawn from the following Conſiderations.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65554:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, that not to keep the Sabbath, but to break and prophane it, is to ſin againſt the Light and the Law of Nature, which prompts the rational Creature to ſet a part ſome time for the Solemn VVorſhip of God, the great Being, in whom he lives, and moves and has his Being, of which the Heathen were ſenſible by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates and Light of Nature, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerv'd to the <hi>Athenians, Acts</hi> 17.28. where he refers to a verſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus</hi> a Greek Poet—<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>—<hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being: For we are alſo his off-ſpring.</hi> Now the Laws of gratitude require ſome grateful Returns to a benefactor, which the Heathen thought themſelves oblig'd to make to God their chief benefactor, but not knowing the true God, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did VVorſhip many; of which they made Images and repreſentations in Wood, and Stone, and Silver, and Gold, to which they inſtituted divine VVorſhip, and Solemn times for the performance of it; in which they were very devout and ſerious, and would not rob their God.</p>
            <p>And, O! how will their blind Devotion ſhame and condemn the indevout, negligent, careleſs Chriſtian: 'Twill undoubtedly at the great day, when the account of all the VVorld ſhall be ſcann'd over, and every one judg'd according to his VVorks: Then will Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the great judge of the VVorld lay open, O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, both thine and the Heathens VVorks. He will then animadvert upon their diligent and blind Devotion, and thy negligence, and zealleſs cold performances. <hi>Here stands a poor blind Heathen, who had only the dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and obſcurer Light of Nature, and yet how devoutly did he fall down to his ſtock and his ſtone, and keep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable the time ſacred to the honour of his Idol; when thou, O prophane Chriſtian, who hadſt the Light of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, didſt tranſgreſs the Laws of thy Maker and Redeemer, and fearleſsly break their bonds aſunder, and caſt away their Cords from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65554:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that not to keep the Sabbath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is to ſin againſt the expreſs Law of our Creator; who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands one day in ſeven to be kept Solemn and ſacred for his ſervice, and will by no means diſpenſe with the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. And what art thou, O man, that durſt break it? Is not he thy Maker, and art not thou his Creature, and conſequently at his diſpoſe? Art not thou accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for all thy actions to him? Didſt thou not receive thy Being, and well Being from him? canſt thou live, or move, or breath without him, and yet doeſt thou act as if thou hadſt received nothing from him, and oweſt nothing to him? Is all thy dependance upon him, and yet wilt thou not at all live to him? Can he ſave thee alive or deſtroy thee in a moment, and yet careſt thou not? Doeſt thou neither value his favour, nor fear his diſpleaſure? Are you not his people and Sheep of his paſture? Is not the inference than natural, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his Gates with thanksgiving, and into his Courts with praiſe, be thankful unto him and bleſs his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider, wherefore did God ſend thee into the World and continue thee in it, what to live as the <hi>Leviathan</hi> in the Water, to take thy paſtime therein, to live to thy ſelf only, yea the vileſt part of thy ſelf, that walking lump of Clay, thy body, while the Soul, thy immortal part is neglected and God forgotten days without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? Remember he whom thou ſinneſt againſt is thy King; and if thou wilt live in Rebellion thou knoweſt not how ſoon he may ſend out his warrant to attack thee, and drag thee to his judgment ſeat; and throw thee into Hell. Why ſhould he any longer ſuffer ſuch a perverſe obſtinate wretch that will not be reclaim'd after frequent warnings and long forbearance, ſuch a harden'd Traytor and Rebel that will offend ſtill, and infect his fellow Subjects, and draw them from their allegiance, ſuch an old accuſtom'd thief, that will ſteal and rob ſtill, and is ripe for Execution: Remember
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65554:16"/>Chriſtians he whom you offend is the great <hi>Landlord</hi> of Heaven and Earth, and you are his Tenants, and Tenants at will too, and the Sabbath is his weekly <hi>Court-day,</hi> whereon he ſummons all his Tenants to come in and pay their Homage and chief Rents, whereby they acknowledge that they hold all under him, and depend for all upon him, and owe all to him. And if you omit your duty, and will not pay your ſuit and ſervice, what can you expect leſs than to be amerc'd and fin'd? And you know not how ſoon be may ſend out his Officers, the Angels, and leavy thoſe fines and Amerciaments on you, and exact it of you: And in what manner is at his pleaſure, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on your Goods or Relations, or Body or Soul; for all is in his power and at his diſpoſe; and he has ſeveral Inſtruments of his wrath to execute his Will. He may ſend the Thief to rob you and ſteal your Goods, and in that Act retaliate your thieviſh tricks, your robbing of God; the falſe dealer to cheat you, and go away with your Goods and Mony, now a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt at Sea, to drown ſome, anon a fire by Land to burn the reſt of your Goods, and demoliſh your Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and turn you out of poſſeſſion; one while he may ſend the Murraine amongſt your Cattle, another while <hi>Blaſting</hi> and <hi>Mildew,</hi> the <hi>Caterpillar, and Palmer-Worm, his Great Army,</hi> as he ſtiles them [<hi>Joel</hi> 2.25.] and Blaſt and devour the Fruits of the Earth, and baffle your hopes and expectations of a plentiful Crop; make <hi>the Heavens</hi> above <hi>braſs,</hi> and the Earth beneath <hi>Iron,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Rain and break off the ſtaff of Bread, and cauſe the <hi>black horſe</hi> to ride through your ſtreets, yea and the <hi>Pale horſe</hi> too, he may ſend the Plague and noiſome Peſtilence, and other Diſeaſes, and afflict you in your perſons and Relations: Now a Child, anon a Brother, now a Father, anon a Husband, or a Wife,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65554:17"/>or a dear Friend may be taken from you and leave you all in tears and ſadneſs. 'Tis not unuſual with God to ſnatch away ſome by death, and that as an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and puniſhment to their offending Relatives. Yea the Fine may be levied on your own perſons that offend, and the payment exacted of you, either by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which takes away your Health, by lameneſs which takes away your ſtrength, by madneſs which takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your Reaſon, or by ſome ſad accident, or ſudden ſtroke which takes away your Life. Or God may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute theſe puniſhments, for temporal inflict ſpiritual ones; a hard heart, and a ſeared Conſcience, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind: which was that ſevere ſpiritual Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which God inflicted on the Heathen for their Pride and Rebellion, and rejecting the knowledge of God, Rom. 1.28. <hi>And even as they did not like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind, to do thoſe things which are not convenient.</hi> Or elſe he may epitomize along ſeries of puniſhments, contract them into that fatal Abridgment and Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of all miſeries, Eternal death.</p>
            <p>That's the ſecond Argument.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider 'tis to ſin againſt the Law, againſt the Obligation of the Blood, and love of our Redeemer, to keep the Chriſtian Sabbath is his Law: And the chief deſign of it is to commemorate the work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which was effected and compleated by the ſhedding of his moſt pretious Blood, which is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt argument of divine Love: Which Sabbath-breakers ſeem to have very little ſenſe of, and very little love and honour for their Redeemer. But let ſuch know that the Blood and Love which they ſpurn at, and trample on will plead againſt them in another day; the Blood of Jeſus if deſpis'd and trodden under foot will ſpeak worſe things than the Blood of <hi>Abel;</hi> the reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65554:17"/>the violated Law of Chriſt will exact a ſeverer puniſhment than the deſpiſed Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> So the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29. <hi>He that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes <hi>Law, died without mercy, under two or three witneſſes,</hi> (ſo did the man that gather'd ſticks on the Sabbath day, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32, &amp;c. a ſmall fault you'll ſay, but being a breach of the Law, and he the firſt violater of it, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith, therefore for example to all others in future times he was ſo ſeverly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but what he did was out of neceſſity; but how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable are they that do needleſs works, and break the Sabbath out of preſumption and contempt of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, and Obligations of the Blood and Love of our Redeemer:) <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy who hath troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfoot the Son of God, and counted the blood of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but perhaps all that has been ſaid is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prevail with ſome. They value not the Law of Nature, nor the Law of their Creator, nor the Blood, nor Love of their Redeemer. They are not fond of the Character of being a good Chriſtian, but they aſpire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that of a good ſubject (though I profeſs 'tis a Riddle to me how he that is not a good Chriſtian can be a good Subject, but) this Title and Character they are proud of and glory in, and deſire above all things to be accounted good Subjects. Well, but tell me, you that are ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of this Title, and are ſo little fond of that of a Chriſtian, is he a good Subject that breaks the Kings Laws? You'l readily anſwer no.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider therefore, which is my fourth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that not to keep the Sabbath, but to break and prophane it, is to break the Kings Law, to treſpaſs againſt the Law of our temporal Governour, which enjoyns the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65554:18"/>pious Obſervation of the Lord's day by repeated ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Parliament under Penalties to be inflicted on the violaters of it. So that in a word, Sabbath-breakers are neither good Chriſtians nor good Subjects.</p>
            <p n="5">5. My Fifth and Laſt Argument is drawn from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and advantages of the due and conſcionable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the day.</p>
            <p>This day is a bleſſed day; <hi>The Lord bleſſed the Seventh day and hallowed it.</hi> 'Tis a day of bleſſings, of many bleſſings, and the cheifeſt and beſt of all, ſpiritual ones, and the pledge of eternal.</p>
            <p>This is the day wherein pardons are ſealed to peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinners, and the Sentence of Guilt and Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reverſed, and Reconciliation ratified in the blood of Chriſt. This is the day that the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth with healing under his wings,</hi> to diſpel and ſcatter the Clouds, that ſit upon the angry face of God's Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to clear up the Heavens above, and make it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene and pleaſant on the Earth beneath, and take off the Sable Mantle, that black and dark covering which over-ſpreads the troubled Breaſts, the aking hearts and afflicted wounded conſciences of Sinners, and give them reſt, and peace, and joy in the comfortable and refreſhing gleams, and illuſtrious ſhine of the light of God's countenance.</p>
            <p>This is the day of feaſting and banqueting for the Soul. Now it Feaſts with Angels and with Saints; yea, with the whole glorious Trinity. <hi>I will come and ſup with him and he with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Souls treaſuring, it's enriching day. It lays up Treaſures where neither Moth nor Ruſt do corrupt, and where Theives cannot break through and ſteal. Now the Soul is enriching it ſelf, growing rich towards God. Now is her attiring day, wherein ſhe buys and puts on her glorious Robes; the white Robe, the Upper Garment of her Saviour's Righteouſneſs, and thoſe inner Linings of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65554:18"/>inherent Holineſs. Theſe ſhe now buys and puts on, that ſhe may be in a readineſs to meet the Bridegroom.</p>
            <p>And this is the Market-day for the buying of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, this ſpiritual Food and Raymment, and the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of theſe Riches. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth</hi> (ſo runs the Royal Style of that gracious Proclamation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.) <hi>Come ye to the water, and he that hath no money, come buy Wine and Milk without money and without price.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. <hi>I counſel thee to buy of me Gold tried in the fire, that thou mayeſt be rich; and white rayment that thou mayeſt be cloathed, and the ſhame of thy nakedneſs do not appear.</hi> And he that neglects the opportunity on the Market day for the buying of this Proviſion for his Soul (for the other days of the Week are taken up in making proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Body, in getting temporal food, and rayment, and riches) he, I ſay, that lets ſlip the opportunity on the Market day for the buying of this Proviſion for his Soul, this ſpiritual food and rayment, and the getting of theſe riches, when, or how will he buy and get them? How can he expect that his Soul ſhould be nouriſhed to eternal Life? How can he be but wretched, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and poor, and blind, and naked?</p>
            <p>Finally, this ſhorter is a pledge, to the due Obſerver, of that longer and eternal Reſt with we expect in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: an Ante-paſt a Preludium of that eternal Sabbath which we hope to celebrate in the other World; that Reſt which the Apoſtle obſerves remains to the people of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. <hi>There remaineth therefore a Reſt to the people of God.</hi> The word in the Greek is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a day or time of Reſt. 'Tis not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies any common reſt, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batical Reſt, a Reſt that has affinity with, a Reſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and conterminous on the temporal Sabbath, which is a type and pledge, and preguſtation of that eternal Sabbath of reſt which remains to the people of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65554:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>God: a reſt infinitely ſatisfactory and delighting, fully compleat and perfect; a reſt from labour and working, from ſinning and ſuffering, from diſeaſes and pains, from cares and fears, from the vanities and vexations of this mortal Life. O let us labour to enter into that reſt, as the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.11. And happy is that man that ſpends the temporal Sabbath of reſt here in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for, and expectation of that eternal Sabbath of reſt hereafter. <hi>Happy is that Servant, whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi> He will bid him enter into a better reſt and joy. He will then take him by the hand and conduct him from the Earthly to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from the material to the Spiritual holy Temple where the Lamb is worſhipped in the Regions of Glory. He will tranſlate him from Reſt on Earth to Reſt in Heaven, from the Company of Saints Militant to the <hi>Chorus</hi> of the Saints Triumphant, from the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities of a temporal Sabbath in the State of Grace to the Celebration of an eternal Sabbath of Reſt in Glory. To which God of his infinite Mercy bring us all for Jeſus ſake, to whom be aſcribed by us, and the whole Church, all Honour, Power, Praiſe, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Glory, now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
